Inventory of the James Barron Papers (1) 1776-1899
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Box 15 (Box-folder 15:1-30)
  - Newspaper reports of the published correspondence of Barron and Decatur, 8-22 April 1820., 6 items. NCl. (Box-folder 15:9)
    The newspaper clippings include the following: American Beacon, 8 April 1820; Norfolk, 11 April 1820; The Gazette, Winchester, 15 April 1820; American Advocate, 22 April 1820; and two undated articles.
  - Newspaper reports of a pamphlet of 26 pages published by the friends of Commo. Decatur containing the letters, which led up to the Barron-Decatur duel, [1820]., 2 items. NCl. (Box-folder 15:10)
  - Newspaper reports of the decision of the Naval Court of Enquiry on Commo. Barron, 13 August 1821., 3 items. (Box-folder 15:11)
  - Newspaper reports of the discovery of the "Rodney Urn" in Philadelphia and its return to Norfolk, where it was placed on display, 1947-1955., 4 items. ADr. (Box-folder 15:12)
    The "Rodney Urn" was silver urn, given to Caesar Rodney, a former Attorney General of the U.S. who had defended James Barron at the Court of Enquiry without pay. The newspaper articles include the following: Norfolk Ledger-Dispatch, 10 January 1947; Norfolk Virginian-Pilot, 14 November 1954; Norfolk Virginian-Pilot, 1 January 1955.
  - The complete issue of the National Gazette and Literary Register, Philadelphia, 26 September 1821., N. (Box-folder 15:13)
    This includes an editorial opinion of the Court of Enquiry upon Commo. Barron.
  - The complete issue of the Norfolk and Portsmouth Herald, 4 July 1823., N. (Box-folder 15:14)
    This contains the obituary of Mrs. Elizabeth Moseley Barron, late wife of Commo. James Barron.
  - The complete issue of the Norfolk and Portsmouth Herald, 18 August 1824., N. (Box-folder 15:15)
    This includes an editorial on the testimonial dinner offered to Commo. James Barron upon his assuming the command of the Philadelphia Naval Yard and his declining of it due to his wish "to avoid all appearance of ostentation or triumph."
  - The complete issue of the American Watchman and Delaware Advertiser, Wilmington, 20 August 1824., N. (Box-folder 15:16)
    This includes an account of the landing of General Lafayette in New York.
  - The complete issue of the Columbian Observer, Philadelphia, 20 August 1824., N. (Box-folder 15:17)
    This includes an editorial on Lafayette, "good man, sincere Patriot, and distinguished Soldier of our Revolution."
  - The complete issue of the Delaware Gazette, Wilmington, 27 August 1824., N. (Box-folder 15:18)
    This includes a report of the visit of General Lafayette to New York, Brooklyn, and New Haven.
  - The complete issue of the United States Gazette, Philadelphia, 23 September 1824., N. (Box-folder 15:19)
    This includes an announcement of the expected arrival of General Lafayette in Philadelphia with the order of Civic Procession.
  - The complete issue of the United States Gazette, Philadelphia, 25 September 1824., N. (Box-folder 15:20)
    This includes reports of the departure of General Lafayette from New York and his reception in Troy, New York.
  - The complete issue of the Philadelphia Gazette and Daily Advertiser, 29 September 1824., N. (Box-folder 15:21)
    This includes an account of the continuing journeys of "The Nation's Guest," General Lafayette.
  - The complete issue of The Philadelphia Gazette and Daily Advertiser, 4 October 1824., N. (Box-folder 15:22)
    This includes an account of the visit of General Lafayette to the Philadelphia Naval Yard, Commo. James Barron, commanding.
  - The complete issue of The New York Gazette and General Advertising, 5 October 1824., N. (Box-folder 15:23)
    This includes an account of the visit of "The Nation's Guest" General Lafayette, to the Philadelphia Naval Yard.
  - The complete issue of The United States Gazette, Philadelphia, 8 October 1824., N. (Box-folder 15:24)
    This includes a report of the visit of General Lafayette to Philadelphia and of his further journey to Chester, Pa., and on to Delaware.
  - The complete issue of the Washington Gazette, 11 December 1824., N. (Box-folder 15:25)
    This includes a report of the reception of General Lafayette by the United States Congress.
  - Newspaper clipping, 22 July 1825., NCl. (Box-folder 15:26)
    Re: Naval Courts, printed in The Herald.
  - Article on the order of Procession for the funeral of Commo. Hull in Philadelphia, 19 February 1843., NCl. (Box-folder 15:27)
  - Renewed discussion of Commo. Barron in the Chesapeake affair, 5 January 1850., 2 items. NCl. (Box-folder 15:28)
  - The complete issue of The American Beacon and Norfolk and Portsmouth Advertiser, 1 May 1851., N. (Box-folder 15:29)
    This includes the obituary of Commo. James Barron.
  - An editorial from The Landmark, Norfolk, founded by James Barron Hope, suggesting that a vessel be named for the late Commo. James Barron, 15 November 1899., NCl. (Box-folder 15:30)
  - Letter - Thomas Truxton, Norfolk, [Virginia] to Capt. James Sever, n.p., 26 April 1800., 1 page. ALS.
    Orders Sever to take over the Chesapeake toward the end of May as Capt. [James] Barron says it will be ready then; he is to take his crew, the marine officer and marines, the master and about thirty seamen, such midshipmen and "pettee officers" as he thinks proper, and two or three warrant officers. The Chesapeake will move down to the Cran[e]y Island. It is essential to get the ship out as early as possible.